William Temple Franklin Papers 1775-1819 Mss.B.F86
American Philosophical Society
- William Temple Franklin Papers, 1775-1790; Mss.B.F86; 4.5 lin. feet
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 May 2; ALS, 2p.; Chaumont, Le Ray de, fils
    Gives an account of his journey and the vessels he saw in port. Was on board the "Bon Homme Richard." Saw Lady Gransby [?] the renowned English beauty. Asks for news about Miss La Bahard and the Brillon family.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 May 13; L.S. 1p.; Grugenot, ------
    Begs him to recommend to his grandfather, Mr. Bartholomew Terasson, who went over to America to carry on his trade of merchant; regrets that he is too busy to enjoy his truly interesting conversation or a game of chess.
  - to William Temple Franklin, [1779.] May 20; N.S. 1p.; Capitaine, -----
    Called to see him and to remind him that the map of the scene of the war in America made by him (Capitaine) is being engraved. Hopes Dr. Franklin and his son will give it their approbation and send some copies to America.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 June 3; ALS, 4p.; Williams 3d, Jonathan
    Is leaving for I'Orient and from there will embark for America. Asks William Temple Franklin to write him of his adventures with the "Nymphs of St. Honoré" and other little anecdotes and news of the day. Requests that some clothing he left at the hotel be forwarded to him.
  - to William Temple Franklin, [ca. 1779] June 16; ALS, 1p.; Cabanis, Pierre Jean Georges. Auteuil
    Recommending a steward; messages from Madame Helvétius and himself.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 June 29; ALS, 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Gives an extract of a letter from Capt. Green relating the capture of a convoy of British vessels and supplies bound from New York to Georgia by the "Warren," the "Queen of France" and "Ranger"; Mr. [William] Carmichael to come to France soon in the "Deane." Has also received a letter from La Corogne [Corunna], Spain, giving an account of an engagement between the American privateer "General Arnold" and an English privateer, in which the latter was sunk.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 June 29; ALS, 1p.; Gourlade, -----.
    Received the case he forwarded and advised M. [Anne César] de la Luzerne; it could not be taken on board the frigate " Du Ploy la Sensible." Will ship it by the "Alliance" or some other vessel.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 July 1; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Wharton, Samuel
    Requesting a copy of the memorial concerning Vandalia.
  - to William Temple Franklin, [ca. 1779] July 1; ALS, 2p.; Capitaine, -----
    Inquires if Marquis de Lafayette's "intendant" has paid what was due to William Temple Franklin.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 July 15; ALS, 3p.; Lloyd, Richard Bennett
    Has received word that his friends in America have collected a considerable sum of money for him and are prepared to honor his drafts. Asks advice as to how he should proceed in the matter. Met Mr. [Sir John] Temple the other evening, he came from Boston by way of Holland.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 July 22; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792
    Has heard from a Captain at Bordeaux, who left Hampton, Va., on May 22d, that he saw three of the enemies' ships of war lying at Norfolk but heard nothing of their exploits, as published in the London Gazette. Does not believe they have blocked up a single river.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 July 27; ALS, 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Refers to his letter to Dr. Franklin about the escaped American prisoners who are in distress at Nantes. Took a particular interest in their cases to counteract the impression there that Dr. Franklin was a cruel, inhuman man, who wantonly left them suffer. S---- has since engaged to pay their landlady out of his own pocket.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 July 29; ALS, 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Enclosing three Loan Office bills for acceptance. Has received a letter from America for John Adams.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Aug. 8; ALS, 1p.; Ross, John
    Requests that a letter for Sweden which Dr. Franklin promised to write, be sent him.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Aug. 9; ALS, 1p.; Alexander, William. St. Germain-en-Laye
    Advising him that the ball to be given by Mme. de Merville has been postponed.
  - to William Temple Franklin, [1779] Aug. 22; A.L. in 3d P. 3p.; Brillon, ------
    He will leave, Tuesday, with M. de Samlot, and he expects him to join them.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Sept. 1; ALS, 1p.; Ross, John
    Heard of his return yesterday. Encloses a letter received from Holland for the Doctor's perusal.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Sept. 2; L.S. 1p.; de Montbarrey, Prince
    Notifying him that the King had sanctioned Comte de Vergennes's proposition to allow him to embark at Havre with the French troops bound for England and wear the uniform of Aide-de-camp.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Sept. 7; ALS, 6p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Delighted that he is to be his Aide-de-camp; his rank and uniform; time of embarkation. No news as yet of the situation, manceuvres and intentions of the two fleets. Anxious for some word of Comte d'Estaing. Believes England to be in a bad way. Enclosing a memoir and an address from a Prussian officer, for his grandfather's perusal.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Sept. 8; ALS, 3p.; de Sorlut, De Court
    Is going to settle in business in Bordeaux and enter into partnership with a large exporting firm. Asks to be given the title of Consul for the United States; would perform the duties free.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Sept. 11; ALS, 2p.; Lloyd, Richard Bennett. Isle of Thanet
    Accounts have arrived in London that the French forces have taken Grenada and of an engagement between the French and British fleets. Asks for the address of Mr. [William] Caslon who brought a letter to London from William Temple Franklin.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Sept. 11; ALS, 2p.; Gimat, -----
    His lodgings will be ready upon his arrival at Havre; hopes for the speedy departure of the expedition.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Sept. 13; ALS, 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Requests him to get as full particulars as possible at Versailles about the Grenada conquest, as Mr. [Alexander John] Alexander has property interests on that island.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Sept. 13; ALS, 1p.; Bache, Richard
    Has received a memorandum of inquiry concerning Henry Dieudonné Drourat. Encloses a letter from him to his father. Chevalier de la Luzerne has not arrived yet, being on his way from Boston. Departure of M. [Conrad Alexandre] Gérard [de Rayneval] universally regretted. Mrs. Bache and himself miss him very much.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Sept. 14; ALS, 2p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    He may remain in Paris for some time yet; his presence not being required at Havre. Is himself going to a country seat near Havre. Alludes to the Empress of Russia's efforts to effect a reconciliation between the belligerents. The expedition against England is still being considered by the Ministry, but doubts if it will be decided upon.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Sept. 16; ALS, 4p.; Bache, Sarah Franklin, 1743-1808
    Is anxiously awaiting the arrival of her father's bust; nothing could be more acceptable to her. Has had several letters recently from her brother, William Franklin; always inquires about his father and his son. Is sending a box of squirrel skins to William Temple Franklin by M. [Conrad Alexander] Gérard [de Rayneval]. Requests him to send her several articles which cannot be bought in America and a doll for her young daughter. Asks also that her father send her several household articles. Mentions the Duffield family, the Misses Clifton, etc.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Sept. 19; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792
    Begs him to accept a picture of Dr. Franklin which he has ordered.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Sept. 20; ALS, 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    With reference to some [Loan Office] bills.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Sept. 20; ALS, 3p.; Deane, Silas, 1737-1789
    Very difficult at present to procure, in America, even the most necessary articles of life and more so curiosities of any kind; tried to get some of the latter for his friends in Paris but without success; money depreciating and merchandise selling at enormous prices. Has heard that his son [Jesse Deane] was spending the holidays with him. Requests the latters to take care of the furniture he left at Passy. Their many enemies and villifiers; every packet brings most outrageous scandal about Dr. Franklin. Is preparing to leave America. Has not seen Mr. [John] Adams since his return; hears he is disgusted at Congress for not appointing him to some Court abroad.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779. Sept. ?.; A.N.S. 1p.; Ross, John
    Requests him to remind Dr. Franklin to write to England about [Capt. Gustavus] Conyngham who is in prison.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Oct. 1; ALS, 2p.; De St. Aubin, -----
    Requests William Temple Franklin to show his portrait of General Washington to the Marquis Lafayette and let him know the latter's opinion of it; as he wishes to put it on sale and send some copies to America. Hears that M. Lafayette is going to have a full size portrait of General Washington made.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Oct. 2; ALS, 3p.; Vaughan, John
    Requests William Temple Franklin to buy him a watch in Paris. Has left Bordeaux, as he found he could not learn French well there. Is going to put lightning rods on a new house built by neighbor of his; asks a few particulars on the matter.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Oct. 11; A.LS. 4p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Thanking him for the engraving of Washington; thinks it the best likeness he has seen in Europe, with the expection of one in his possession, taken from the original owned by Mr. [John] Hancock; intends to have an engraving made from this, after a drawing by the famous [Charles Nicolas] Cochin. Has received a letter from Capt. [John Paul] Jones in regard to [Capt. Pierre] Landais; regrets disputes between men fighting for the same cause. Begs for American news. Has great hopes of Comte d'Estaing's expedition. In case of embarking, will let him know in due time to get a Havre.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Oct. 14; ALS, 2p.; Torris, John
    Asking for two commissions for the privateers "Black Prince" and "Black Princess." Refers to reported capture of two cutters commanded by [Comte Sutton] de Clonard and de Roquefeuille, off the Lizard.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Oct. 15; ALS, 1p.; Breton, Alexandre
    Inquiring about a letter he sent for [Jonathan] Williams, [Jr.], of
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Oct. 19; ALS, 1p.; Montfort, Comte de
    Requests him to read his educational plan or program submitted to Dr. Franklin and give his opinion on the English translation of it.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Oct. 22; ALS, 2p.; Laneuville, Louis Pierre Panot Lombart, chevalier de, 1744-ca.1800
    Sends three letters to be forwarded to Chevalier de la Luzerne, Chevalier D'Anmours and Mr. [John] Bradford. Is uneasy about his baggage and effects which were to be sent him by the latter.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Oct. 26; ALS, 3p.; Laneuville, Louis Pierre Panot Lombart, chevalier de, 1744-ca.1800
    Requests him to induce Dr. Franklin to write to Congress about his brother who is serving in the United States.
  - to William Temple Franklin, [1779] Oct. 29; ALS, 4p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Asking for various maps of Great Britain.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Oct. 31; ALS, 1p.; Laneuville, Gen. Chevalier de
    Inviting him to dinner.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Nov. 1; ALS, 4p.; Vaughan, John
    Came to France to learn the language and get experience in business. Now knows the language and proposes to go over to America and settle there before the war is over. Asks that his plan be submitted to Dr. Franklin for advice.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Nov. 1; ALS, 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Asking William Temple Franklin to take care of his horse and dispose of him at the first opportunity.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Nov. 3; A. N. S. 1p.; Alexander, William
    Sending Jonathan William [Jr.]'s horse.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Nov. 17; ALS, 1p.; Montfort, Count
    Inquiring about the report of the taking of New York and the defeat of Gen. Prevost by Gen. [Benjamin] Lincoln.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Nov. 18; ALS, 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Enclosing a letter for M. Suard. Inquires about the order from Congress for goods. Thinks [Le Ray] de Chaumont seems to prefer l'Orient to Nantes for shipping goods, but claims the latter port is more advantageous. Inquires about his new relations [the Alexander family] and [Thomas] Walpole.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Nov. 22; ALS, 1p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre
    Is glad to hear Dr. Franklin is recovered. Will call on him Wednesday morning.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Nov. 31; ALS, 2p.; Capitaine, -----
    Inquiring if his letters and some of his maps have been forwarded to the United States as requested.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Dec. 7; ALS, 3p.; Caslon, William
    Requests him to send him several "rolls and pots of pomatum."
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Dec. 10; ALS, 2p.; Lloyd, Richard Bennett
    Has learned that William Temple Franklin has been married to one of the Miss Alexanders. Offers his congratulations. Hears that Mr. [Jonathan] Williams, [Jr.], has married into the same family. Wishes to know which of the young ladies is now Mrs. Franklin and which one Mrs. Williams. Encloses a letter to be delivered to Mr. [William] Carmichael as soon as he arrives in Europe.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ca.1779.; ALS, 1p.; Amchaga, M. d'
    There are many rumors here about Mr. d'Estaing. He (d'Amchaga) will dine with Mr. Franklin on the 19th.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Dec. 11; L.S. 2p.; Holker, Jean.
    Has heard from Mr. [Jonathan] Williams, [Jr.] that he saw the Captain of the ship "Comité." Latter's account of Comte d'Estaing's movements unreliable. M. [Conrad Alexandre] Gérard [de Rayneval]'s arrival expected to any movement. Has received several letters from his son up to Sept. 18th containing no important news.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Dec. 12; L.S. 3p.; Moëballe, Col. Nicholas George. Vitry
    Is seriously ill and without friends or money. Begs that Dr. Franklin send him a few louis until he can get a remittance from Holland.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Dec. 17; ALS, 2p.; Capitaine, -----. Mezières
    Asks for any news he has about Capt. [John Paul] Jones and Lieut. Col. [Antoine Félix] Wuibert. Will call on his return to Paris to make arrangements for the coming campaign.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Dec. 18; ALS, 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Enclosing bills on the Commissioners for acceptance. Inquires about the order for goods from Congress.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Dec. 18; L.S. 2P.; Bezanger, -----
    Offers to supply wine.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Dec. 20; ALS, 2p.; Digges, Thomas
    He is sending him, by way of Amsterdam, a box containing maps ordered by him of counties and towns in England and Ireland.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Dec. 21; ALS, 3p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Has heard from M. de Laneuville that some papers have arrived from America for Dr. Franklin. Asks if they contain any news of interest. Inquires about Gen. Washington's health. Is very anxious to hear from M. [Conrad Alexandre] Gérard [de Rayneval].
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Dec. 21; ALS, 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Encloses bills on the Commissioners. Has heard nothing about the "Confederacy." Fears that she has met with the same fate as poor [Lambert] Wickes in the "Reprisal." Wishes to hear about Congress's orders for goods and his new relations' affairs.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Dec. 21; L.S. 2P.; Ross, John
    Encloses for acceptance twenty-three Continental Loan Office notes drawn on Dr. Franklin. As Congress has ordered his accounts to be paid, hopes some plan will be adopted by Dr. Franklin for making a settlement; his advances having exposed him too much.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Dec. 22; ALS, 2p.; Laneuville, Louis Pierre Panot Lombart, chevalier de, 1744-ca.1800
    Thanking him for the news about his brother [Normiont de Laneuville] who is serving in the United States. Sent the letter and newspaper containing the article to Marquis Lafayette; has asked the latter to have the letter and article published in the European papers.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Dec. 25; ALS, 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Enclosing bills on the Commissioners for acceptance. Requests him to reply for Dr. Franklin to his letters.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Dec. 29; ALS, 1p.; Moëballe, Col. Nicholas George
    Thanks Dr. Franklin and William Temple Franklin for assisting him in need. Remits two louis in payment of the sum loaned to him.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 Dec. 31; ALS, 2p.; Petrie, S
    Requests him to procure the release on parole of Geo. Taylor, Lieutenant of the British privateer "Chance," in prison at Bayonne; also of John Craig a passenger on the ship "Matty" of Glasgow.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ca.1779.; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Monsieur and Madame de Boulainvillers
    Invitation to the wedding of Madamoiselle de Boulainvillers and Le Vicomte de Clermont Tonnere.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ca.1779.; ALS, 1p.; Breton, Alexandre
    Wishes to know if Mr. [Jonathan] Williams, [Jr.] has returned to
  - to William Temple Franklin, ca.1779.; ALS, 1p.; Brown, -----
    Thanks him for his letter, will call to see him at the first opportunity.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ca.1779.; ALS, 1p.; Brown, -----
    Enclosing a letter to Dr. Franklin from Mr. Pollard, and an answer to the letter he dictated for him to the gentlemen at
  - to William Temple Franklin, ca.1779.; ALS, 2p.; Cabanis, Pierre Jean Georges. Auteuil
    Recommending a brave sailor who wishes to obtain a commission from the United States to fit out a privateer and cruise against the English.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ca.1779.; ALS, 1p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Encloses some drafts, bills and gazettes, if these are correct they are to be returned as soon as possible. Tomorrow is the last day for the payment of [John D.] Schweighauser's drafts.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ca.1779 March; ALS, 2p.; Hersaut, -----
    Asking his protection to obtain a position.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ca.1779.; ALS, 2p.; Laneuville, Louis Pierre Panot Lombart, chevalier de, 1744-ca.1800
    Enclosing letters with request that they be forwarded to America.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ca.1779.; ALS, 1p.; De Moullaine M. fils
    Has heard that General [Aug.ine] Prevost has met the same fate as Burgoyne; if this should not be known at present, he will be discreet.
    (In french.)
  - to William Temple Franklin, ca.1779.; Mem. 1p.; Mouret, Prosper
    Wishes to go to the United States to engage in his trade as printer.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ca.1779.; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Petrie, S
    Invites him to call on him.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780 Jan. 1; ALS, 3p.; Vaughan, John
    Having received a letter from his brother, he decides to remain abroad to wait the results of the West India operations.
  - to William Temple Franklin., 1780 Jan. 1; ALS, 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Thanks him for his trouble about the horse; has sent some patterns for Dr. Franklin's inspection.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780 Jan. 4; ALS, 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Encloses Loan Office bills of exchange for acceptance; the arrival of two Captains from Philadelphia at l'Orient and of a boat from Baltimore at Bordeaux.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780 Jan. 5; ALS, 1p.; Laneuville, Louis Pierre Panot Lombart, chevalier de, 1744-ca.1800
    Invitation to a ball.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780 Jan. 8; ALS, 1p.; Laneuville, Louis Pierre Panot Lombart, chevalier de, 1744-ca.1800
    The ball has been postponed to Sunday. Asks for news of the arrival of Mr. J[ohn] Adams.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780 Jan. 8; ALS, 2p.; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
    The opinion of Baron de Steding on the conduct of the American soldiers.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780 Jan. 8; ALS, 2p.; Vaughan, John
    Thanks him for all his trouble and for the condescending goodness of his grandfather; encloses fifteen louis for the watch, which has arrived safely.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780 Jan. 10; ALS, 1p.; Ross, John
    Requests the return of "sundry bills" to him at Nantes; expresses anxiety about the overdue "Confederacy"; no news of Mr. [John] Adams.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780 Jan. 11; ALS, 1p.; Laneuville, Louis Pierre Panot Lombart, chevalier de, 1744-ca.1800
    Accepts invitation for dinner and will go with him to the ball.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780 Jan. 18; ALS, 3p.; Prevon, -----
    Asks him to see that M. [Le Ray] de Chaumont pays the bill for the wood.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780 Jan. 18; ALS, 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Enclosing a letter for Dr. Franklin, to be presented if proper.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780 Jan. 22; ALS, 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Requesting a blank privateer commission for Capt. Boardman of the schooner "Betsey," Walter Peter and Co., owners.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780 Jan. 24; ALS, 1p.; Laneuville, Louis Pierre Panot Lombart, chevalier de, 1744-ca.1800
    Owing to illness, the ball is postponed until the 31st; invites him to dinner on that date.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780 Jan. 25; ALS, 2p.; Ross, John
    Considers the Resolve of Congress of Aug. 11, 1778, sufficient authority for the discharge of his claim against the United States; Captain [John] Green lost his vessel through the carelessness of his pilot; offers to take dispatches to America when he leaves with Captain [Thomas] Bell.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780 Jan. 28; ALS, 1p.; Laneuville, Louis Pierre Panot Lombart, chevalier de, 1744-ca.1800
    Requests some India rubber for a lady of his acquaintance; regrets that he cannot be with them on Monday.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780 Feb. 1; ALS, 1p.; Laneuville, Louis Pierre Panot Lombart, chevalier de, 1744-ca.1800
    An invitation to a ball and a dinner on the 7th; also an invitation from some ladies for the 6th.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780 Feb. 1; ALS, 2p.; Scott, George
    Sends his servant for the pass; urges him to write to Dr. [John] P[ringle?] and tells how to send his letter so as to avoid its being opened in London, since ministerial writers are ready to abuse the Doctor.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780 Feb. 1; ALS, 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Enclosing some bills to be accepted.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780 Feb. 8; ALS, 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Requests a commission or letter of marque for Captain [Samuel] Smith of the "Kensington."
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780 Feb. 8; ALS, 1p.; Scott, George
    An invitation to dinner.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780 Feb. 11; ALS, 2p.; Laneuville, Louis Pierre Panot Lombart, chevalier de, 1744-ca.1800
    An invitation to dinner from him and his father; they would also like to have Dr. Franklin.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780 Februrary 11; ALS, 1p.; Jones, Ezra.